מזל טוב. Mazel tov.
Today is the ninth day in the עומר. Omer. Is that right?
All right.
I don't even remember what I had for breakfast. I'm supposed to
remember what I counted for ספירה Sefira last night. Okay,
today's דף יומי Daf Yomi today is נ"ב Nun-Beis 52 and we
pick up in the middle of נ"א עמוד ב'. Nun-Aleph Amud-Beis. We
are in the middle of רבא's Rava position that קידושין שאינה מסורה
לביאה. Kiddushin She'eina Mesura L'via. It's a קידושין, Kiddushin, although קידושין, Kiddushin,
as I mentioned yesterday, is the stage that occurs a good deal
before the נישואין, Nisuin, before the marriage is consummated. So nevertheless,
if the קידושין Kiddushin cannot ultimately translate into the couple being able
to have sex, according to רבא, Rava, it is not a good
קידושין. Kiddushin. Now and again to remind you that says, as תוספות
Tosfos already points out, there are cases where they're not allowed to
have sex like it's one of the איסורי לאוין Isurei Lavim like
ממזר Mamzer or something of that
nature, כהן Kohen and a גרושה. Gerusha. For some reason that's not
included; we're only looking at the איסורי כרת. Isurei Kareis. And the
specific example, and of course on the other hand everybody agrees that
קידושין Kiddushin which was a חייב כרת Chayav Kareis does not take
effect. Somebody tries to marry his sister, it doesn't take effect. So
the issue though is that the קידושין Kiddushin should be good but
because you don't know something, it can never allow for sex. So
a person marries one of two sisters, he doesn't know which one,
and therefore רבא's Rava contention is that it's not that both of
them require a גט מספק, Get mi'safek, neither of them require a
גט Get because he can't have sex with either one because that
might be his wife's sister. So because of that doubt does not
allow it ever to allow for sex to take place, the קידושין
Kiddushin itself is fundamentally not good. That's רבא's Rava position, קידושין שאינה
מסורה לביאה. Kiddushin She'eina Mesura L'via. אביי Abaye disagrees. So far all
of the evidence has been against רבא, Rava, but רבא's Rava managed
of course to respond to the texts and now we sort of
continue with that discussion. So now the גמרא Gemara picks up in
the following place, we're on נ"א עמוד ב' Nun-Aleph Amud-Beis and it
says the following: תא שמע: Ta Shma: מי שיש
לו, Mi Sheyeish Lo,
it's the beginning of a line, it's about 15 lines down in
the wide lines, starts with an asterisk, yeah, about 13 lines down.
מי שיש לו, Mi Sheyeish Lo, okay? So here's a ברייתא: Braisa:
מי שיש לו שתי כיתי בנות, Mi Sheyeish Lo Shtei Kitei Banot,
somebody has two sets of daughters,
meaning he has daughters from two wives and from each wife his
first wife and his second wife and each wife he has two
daughters. משתי נשים, MiShtei Nashim, from two wives. ואמר: V'amar: קידשתי את
בתי הגדולה ואיני יודע, Kidashti Et Biti Hagdola V'eini Yodea, and I
married my older daughter to this man but I forget which daughter
I married. I remember saying it would be my older daughter but
I don't remember what I meant by that. ואיני יודע, V'eini Yodea,
I don't know, אם גדולה שבגדולות, im Gdola ShebaGdolot, if I meant
my oldest one from the first wife, okay, ואם גדולה שבקטנות, v'im
Gdola ShebaKtanot, or the older daughter from the second wife. The גדולות
Gdolot are the older kids and the קטנות Ktanot are the younger
kids, right? Because let's say he had these two wives in stages.
Okay, so an older one from the older group or the older
one from the younger group. Or there's a third possibility: אם קטנה
שבגדולות, im Ktanah ShebaGdolot, maybe I meant even a younger one from
the older group when I said older daughter, I meant
one of my older daughters as opposed to from my second wife's
daughters. שהיא גדולה מן הגדולה שבקטנות, SheGdolah Min HaGdolah ShebaKtanot, because at
least the youngest one from my first wife is older than the
oldest one from my second wife. So anyway, I could have meant
any of these things. כולן אסורות, Kulan Asurot, all, right, but not
the youngest of the youngest ones. כולן אסורות, Kulan Asurot, all of
these daughters
are possibly married to this man and they all need a גט,
Get, חוץ מקטנה שבקטנות, chutz miKtanah ShebaKtanot, with the one exception of
the youngest daughter of the youngest wife; that clearly I could not
have meant when I said the oldest daughter. דברי רבי מאיר, Divrei
Rabbi Meir,
that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. So the point is that
here all of the daughters are married מספק misafek except the youngest
one, even though it's קידושין שאינה מסורה לביאה, Kiddushin She'eina Mesura L'via,
because the חתן Choson would never be able to have sex with
any one of them because it might be his wife's sister, right?
So therefore, it's exactly this case, marrying one sister without knowing who,
and it says that it works. So the גמרא Gemara says, הכא
במאי עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, what are we talking about? And his
father doesn't know which of his daughters it is. Right. הכא במאי
עסקינן, hacha b'mai askinan, what are we talking about? כשהוכרו ולבסוף נתערבו.
Kshehukru u'levasof nisarvu. No, no, no, it's not that the father never
knew at the outset what he meant. It's that he knew who
he meant at the outset and then he forgot. So it was
known, it was recognized, and then it got mixed up. So in
that case, it was קידושין Kiddushin מסורה לביאה Mesura L'via at the
moment of the קידושין, Kiddushin, he knew who he had in mind
and he only forgot afterwards. Of course one wonders like, is it
the type of a יש ברירה, yesh breira, did the חתן Choson
also know who he had in mind and the חתן Choson also
forgot, or the חתן Choson said 'whichever one you pick, that's fine
by
me' and that worked then? Anyway, but okay, it was known initially
and then it was forgotten. So initially the קידושין Kiddushin was חל
chal because at the moment of the קידושין, Kiddushin, it was known
who it was talking about. דייקא נמי, Deika Nami, that also can
be
understood, a careful reading of the words proves this, דקתני d'ktani איני
יודע. eini yodea. I don’t know, I currently don’t know which one
I referred to. ולא קתני אינו ידוע, velo ktani eino yaduia, it’s
not known, like it was never known. Okay, שמע מינה, shema mina,
so that’s a good proof. So it’s not a good, so this
case is not relevant because this case is not that it was
never known, but that it was forgotten. אי הכי ee hachi says
the Gemara, that’s true. מה לממרא, mai lemeimra, what’s the chidush of
the Mishnah? I mean the chidush could be that according to Rabbi
Meir, that we think that Gedola could mean any one of those
girls. But anyway, the Gemara says לאפוקי מדבי רבי יוסי, le'apokei mid'bei
Rabbi Yose, דאמר de'amar לא מחית איניש נפשיה לספיקא. lo machis inish
nafshiei lisefeika. Yes, it’s for, because Rabbi Meir’s position is different from
Rabbi Yose’s. Rabbi Yose would say in that case, if you said
oldest daughter and that’s all you could remember is oldest, we assume
you meant the oldest of the oldest group. Like you would not
allow yourself to have such a doubt, to really get that degree
confused about which daughter you married. So if you’re telling yourself and
reminding yourself remember, if I forget everything just remember it was my
oldest daughter. So you’re going to remember that if you really mean
the oldest of the old. If that idea older daughter, you know,
is a confusing one for you and ambiguous one for you, then
you would have ensured that you would have remembered more specifically. Okay,
so if the only thing you can remember is older daughter we
assume you meant it in the way that clearly identifies which girl
you’re talking about, and you would not allow yourself to enter into
such doubt. So for him you mean the oldest. קא משמע לן
דמחית איניש נפשיה לספיקא, ka mashma lan demachis inish nafshiei lisefeika, nah
people can let them, will allow themselves, not a good thing, but
they will allow themselves to enter into this space of doubt. And
therefore he could have in his mind oldest and not be so
clear what he meant by oldest. That’s an assumption. You know, that
assumption means that under any circumstances where a person is like doing
something that they then need to remember afterwards you assume that they
would never really ever forget. Yeah, I’m not saying he was saying
they would never forget, but if there was something you remembered we’re
going to assume it means the most specifying thing that it could
mean as opposed to as opposed to, right, the possibility of the
vagueness. All right, תא שמע ta shema come and hear. So anyway
so we got rid of that one. That one was that it
was initially it was known. תא שמע ta shema מי שקידש אחת
משתי אחיות mi shekidesh achas mishtei achayos ואינו יודע איזה קידש. ve'eino
yodeia eizeh kidesh. So it’s going to be a similar type of
a case. Somebody married one of two sisters, he doesn’t know which
one he married. Now again obviously we’re laying the groundwork for a
similar answer, he knew and he forgot, but we’re going to assume
it means he never knew which one he married. Okay, so he
says I’m going to marry one of you and I don’t know,
you know, whichever one of you catches the Kiddushin or something. I
don’t know how he did it, but somehow we assume it meant
that it was some way, right, or something like that I guess.
Or he did it with the father and he didn’t know who
the father had in mind. Anyway we assume it means that he
never knew which one he married. Okay, that’s why it’s going to
be a question on Rava.
נותן גט לזו וגט לזו. nosein get lazo veget lazo. He has
to give a get to each one because each one is safek
married to him. Ah, you see it proves again against Rava that
it works, so even though you don’t know which one you married
and it’s never possible to have sex. The Gemara says no, הכא
במאי עסקינן כשהוכרו לבסוף ונשרפו. hacha bemai askinan keshehukaru levasof venisrefu. No,
no, no, again we’re talking about a case that he knew and
then he forgot, and I guess they forgot as well. You’d have
to try to figure out what the circumstances are there. Anyway, דייקא
נמי דקתני deika nami dekatani
maybe they were twins, דייקא נמי דקתני deika nami dekatani איני יודע
eini yodeia
I don’t know currently ולא קתני velo katani אינו ידוע eino yadua,
it is not known. Okay, so אי הכי ee hachi says the
Gemara ah amazing, אי
הכי ee hachi says the Gemara מה לממרא mai lemeimra again what’s
the chidush if it’s mamash that he knew and he forgot, of
course he has to give each of them a get, thank you
so much. So the Gemara says סיפא איצטריכא ליה seifa itztricha lei
you need it for the end. מת ולא אח, meis velo ach,
so he died, this guy who is married to one of two
possible sisters and he doesn’t know which one.
And he has a brother, so now one of these girls, women,
whatever, need חליצה chalitza or יבום, yibum, but we don’t know which
one. So let’s see, so what’s the brother going to do? חולץ
לשתיהן, choleitz lishteihen,
the brother has to do chalitza for both of them. Did I
skip a line? מת ולא אח אחד meis velo ach echad he
has one brother, no, חולץ לשתיהן choleitz lishteihen he has to do
chalitza for both of them because one of them is his brother’s
widow. Okay, היו לו שנים hayu lo shnayim
now let’s say he had two brothers, אחד חולץ ואחד מייבם, echad
choleitz ve'echad miyabeim,
one of the brothers does chalitza to one sister and the other
can do yibum with the other. אם קדמו וכנסו אין מוציאין אותם
מידם im kadmu vechanu ein motzi'in osam miyadam
and if they both married both sisters then you let them keep
them. Why? What’s the scenario? The scenario is like this. Okay,
you have these two sisters, okay, and you’ve got the two brothers,
right?
Now you don’t know which one is the one that requires yibum
or chalitza, okay? So if you do a chalitza, let’s say you
do chalitza and then this guy does yibum, okay? So he’s got
two brothers. Now let’s say, well let’s start this way, let’s say
there was no chalitza, why in a case of even one, let’s
even in the case of one, why does he have to do
chalitza with both? Why not just go ahead
and And do יבום yibum with one of them? Why can't he
just do marry this sister? Because maybe this is really his sister-in-law,
and if this is his sister-in-law, what does that make this woman
to him? Anybody remember their יבמות? Yevamos? אחות, achos, no, אחות חלוצתו
achos chalutzato
or אחות זקוקתו, achos zekukato,
right? Right. He has a זיקה zikah if if this is the
real sister-in-law, he's got a זיקה zikah to her which makes her
his quasi-wife.
Okay, so to do marry this would be אחות זקוקתו achos zekukato
or זקוקתו. zekukato. Anyway and if he did now, if he let's
say did חליצה, chalitzah, so fine, do חליצה chalitzah to one, okay,
and יבום yibum and marry the other one. Well okay, if this
was not the wife that would work. The brother's wife, the חליצה
chalitzah would be meaningless and then this would be יבום. yibum. Okay,
that would be fine. But if this was the actual dead brother's
wife, then this then this would be אחות חלוצתו, achos chalutzato, which
is no good, okay? That's sort of like the sister of his
ex-wife. Okay, so that's why he has to do חליצה chalitzah to
both. Okay, that's why now let's say there are two brothers. If
there are two brothers, why can one do יבום yibum and one
do חליצה? chalitzah? Okay, because let's look at the possibilities. The first
possibility is that this is actually the widow. Okay, so then that's
fine, that's יבום yibum and then this is a meaningless act, okay?
Everybody with me? Okay, let's say this is the widow. So this
did a חליצה, chalitzah, fine, that's off. He's doing the יבום. yibum.
He is no longer אחות חלוצתו. achos chalutzato. אחות חלוצתו achos chalutzato
is only the woman that you yourself did חליצה chalitzah to, okay?
So without the חליצה, chalitzah, they would both have a זיקה zikah
to her, right? Before חליצה chalitzah is done, they both have a
זיקה zikah to her. Once the חליצה chalitzah is done, that removes
the זיקה zikah and now this is not אחות חלוצתו achos chalutzato
because he's not the one that did חליצה. chalitzah. That's how come
one does חליצה chalitzah and one does יבום. yibum. Now, so you
have to have חליצה chalitzah first then. You have to have חליצה
chalitzah first, exactly. If you didn't do חליצה chalitzah first, it would
be אחות זקוקתו achos zekukato or זקוקתו. zekukato. Anyway, okay, let's say
they both married, okay, כנסו, kinsu, which is I don't know sort
of יבום yibum but one is and one isn't. One of them
did something wrong, okay? If this one let's say was if this
one was let's say the sister, right? The wife if this was
if this was the wife, okay, then when he did the יבום
yibum because first when he married her first, he was marrying אחות
זקוקתו, achos zekukato, okay? Right? Wait, no, one did יבום, yibum, the
other did יבום? yibum? They both did יבום, yibum, okay? So the
one who actually got the right widow, got the widow, he was
okay. It's the sequence. Process. Yeah, he was okay. But the one
who what?
But the one who didn't get the widow, right, was having sex
with אחות זקוקתו, achos zekukato, correct? Okay. Unless it was done exactly
at the same time? Yeah, fine, then maybe then it could be
different because then it would remove the זיקה. zikah. But if the
first guy if the first guy was with the first woman and
that was not the actual widow, then it would have been אחות
זקוקתו. achos zekukato. But once they're already married, okay, since the whole
idea of אחות זקוקתו achos zekukato is only דרבנן derabbanan and by
now the זיקה zikah has gone off anyway, so once they're already
married, we let them stay married, okay? So that's the הלכה halachah
in כנסו, kinsu, once they already got married,
אין מוציאין אותם מידם. ein motzi’in osam mi-yadam. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, ודווקא. u-davka. So now... okay, so this
is
what so this is why, even though it was a case of
this is why we needed to teach this ברייתא, braisa, okay? Meaning
yes, it's an easy case in terms of the issue of קידושין
שאינם מסורים לביאה. kiddushin she-einam mesurim le-vi'ah. We knew which sister it
was and we forgot. So that's not the חידוש chiddush that you
need to give each one a גט get or you need to
do a חליצה chalitzah for each one. The חידוש chiddush is this
more complicated case about two brothers, one does a חליצה chalitzah and
one does a יבום, yibum, okay? And right now the גמרא... Gemara...
right. ודווקא מחלץ והדר יבומי. davka michlatz ve-hadar yabumi. Now you have
to first do a חליצה chalitzah and then do the יבום. yibum.
אבל יבומי והדר מחלץ, aval yabumi ve-hadar michlatz, if one brother does
the יבום yibum first and then the other does the חליצה, chalitzah,
לא, lo, no, דקפגע באחות זקוקתו de-ka paga be-achos zekukato because then
the one who did the יבום yibum first, he might have the
sister of the widow and that would be אחות זקוקתו achos zekukato
if he did it before the חליצה chalitzah was done. Okay, so
anyway we needed to tell you a הלכה halachah in יבום, yibum,
not to tell you a הלכה halachah about קידושין שאינם מסורים לביאה.
kiddushin she-einam mesurim le-vi'ah. The case could be you knew which woman
it was and then you got it mixed up. תא שמע, ta
shema, we're going to do another case just like this. שנים שקידשו
שתי אחיות וזה אינו יודע איזו קידש וזה אינו יודע איזו קידש.
shnayim she-kidshu shtei achayot ve-zeh eino yodei'a eizo kiddesh ve-zeh eino yodei'a
eizo kiddesh. Two people, not brothers, marry two sisters. Each one married
one of them, they don't know each one got one, they don't
know which got which, okay?
Again, we're assuming it means they never knew, and then it's going
to be they knew and they forgot.
Each woman needs to get a גט, get, each man let's say
it that way, which is the way of saying it. Each man
has to give a גט get to both women because I might
be married to Rachel or Leah, so I have to give Rachel
and Leah a גט, get, but Rachel and Leah can't go get
married now because they might have, each one of them might have
been married to the other guy, so each man has to give
two גיטין gittin to, has to give
a גט get to each of the two women.
Okay, so you see again but the קידושין kiddushin took effect. הכא
נמי שכולא בסוף נסתרוו, Hacha nami shekula besof nistarvu, no, it was
initially known which woman I married and then it was forgotten. דיקא
נמי דקתני אינו יודע, Diyka nami diktani eino yodeiah, I don't know,
ולא קתני velo katani אינו ידוע, eino yadua it is not known.
שמע מינה, Shema mina,
that is a good proof. אי הכי מאי למימר, Yachi mai lemeimar,
so what's the חידוש? chiddush? Of course if I might be married
to one of two women, I have to give each one of
them a גט. get. No, סיפא איצטריכא, seifa itzricha, you need it
for the end. מת, Meis,
if the guy who married or both of the guys died, ולזה
אח ולזה אח, veleh ach veleh ach, and they each leave a
surviving brother. זה חולץ לשתיהם וזה חולץ לשתיהם, Zeh choletz lishteihem vezeh
choletz lishteihem, each of the brothers does חליצה chalitzah to each of
the two women. לזה אחד ולזה שנים, Lezeh echad ulezeh shenayim,
one guy has one brother and one guy has two brothers. I'm
sure while reading this you're saying, oh, I so miss יבמות, Yevamos,
I'm so glad we're doing this again. Okay, האחד חולץ לשתיהם, ha'echad
choletz lishteihem,
so brother number one does חליצה chalitzah to Rachel and Leah. והשנים,
Vehashenayim, now the two brothers of the second guy, אחד חולץ ואחד
מיבם. echad choletz ve'echad meyabem. Okay,
so basically in this case, right, so here you've got, right, these
two, okay.
This is guy A and he's got two brothers, and this is
guy B and he's only got one brother, okay?
Now they both die. Okay, so this guy does חליצה chalitzah to
both. Okay, now after doing חליצה chalitzah to both, he walks off.
Okay, he's off, meaning this guy is B's brother, okay? This is
A prime and A double prime.
Okay, so anyway, so after B prime there does חליצה chalitzah to
both, any connection that A had to either women totally has gone
away. He's off the scene. Now you're left with like what we
had before, one guy, right, two brothers, okay. So wait, did we
have two brothers before? We only had one brother. Anyway, it doesn't
matter. So in this case, right, one does חליצה chalitzah to one
woman and one does יבום yibbum to the other, and you're good.
Right? Again, you can't just start by doing יבום yibbum because it
might be אחות זקוקתו, achot zekukato, so you have to do a
חליצה chalitzah and a יבום yibbum like we had before. So the
only thing that's introduced is you have to start though with B
removing himself from the scene. Okay, now if B did not remove
himself from the scene initially and these guys started and one guy
did a חליצה chalitzah and one guy did a יבום, yibbum, okay,
before B prime here did his חליצות, chalitzas, what problem would you
have? Okay, if he did a חליצה, chalitzah, okay, if he did
חליצה chalitzah and he did יבום, yibbum, right, they should be okay
because, okay, if this turns out to be the actual widow, you
know, A's widow,
if this turned out to be A's widow, then this was just
totally, totally nothing, right? Marrying
what? Right? Right, that's just a regular קידושין. kiddushin. Right, if this
actually was, if this actually was, wait, no, no, no, wait, if
this was A's widow, then that's, oh, then the חליצה chalitzah removed
the זיקה zika and then it's no longer אחות זקוקתו, achot zekukato,
then you're fine. If this wasn't A's widow, then this is meaningless
and this is a good יבום. yibbum. Everything is fine, right? One
minute. So that's why חליצה chalitzah then יבום yibbum works. But if
B hadn't removed himself from the scene, one of these women would
be B's widow and therefore B's widow would be marrying some other
guy before she got her necessary חליצה. chalitzah. Okay, that's considered the
איסור issur of יבמה לשוק. yevamah lashuk. One of these women is
waiting for a חליצה chalitzah from B, right, and she's yet marrying
one of these guys. So this חליצה chalitzah has to take place
first and get him off the scene before we can go back
to what we had before. Wait, let's just read that. Okay, now
the גמרא Gemara says אינקשו וקינשו אין מוציאין מידם, inkishu vekinshu ein
motzi'in miyadam, but again if they both do יבום, yibbum, we let
it stay because then the זיקה zika gets removed. דוקא מיחלץ והדר
יבומי, Davka michlatz vadar yabumei, that's only if the B guy first
did his חליצה chalitzah and then we let the A brothers do
their חליצה chalitzah and יבום. yibbum. אבל יבומי והדר מיחלץ לא, Aval
yabumei vadar michlatz lo, but if the A guys would do their
יבום yibbum חליצה chalitzah thing and only then the B guy would
do his חליצה, chalitzah, that wouldn't work, דקפגע ביבמה לשוק, dekappaga beyevamah
lashuk, so then one of these guys is marrying a woman who
is a יבמה yevamah and she's going out into the marketplace, that's
יבמה לשוק yevamah lashuk before she got her necessary חליצה chalitzah from
B. Okay, so this is basically telling you the sequence. Okay. First
B's got to do חליצה chalitza for both to get off the
scene to allow one of these guys to do a יבום. yibum.
But if he hasn't, then one of these women is going to
be required
obligated in a חליצה chalitza and be marrying somebody else. So that's
what this this is teaching us, but as a base it is
not teaching us the issue about קידושין שאינו ראוי לביאה, Kiddushin she-eino
ra-uy l'viah, we'd be talking about a case that it was known
who the wife was and then it was forgotten. But if it
was never known, according to רבא Rava the קידושין Kiddushin would not
be חל. chal. Yes. Wait, so even without any of this חליצה,
chalitza, both of them would still be אסור assur to a כהן,
kohen, maybe one of them was was married. Yeah, it's like a
ספק חליצה safek chalitza or ספק safek no no, that would be
a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. But this from אירוסין, erusin, right? No
no, there's a כהן kohen could marry her. But now that חליצה
chalitza is no no, I mean the she's no, it's a ספק
חליצה. safek chalitza. An אלמנה almanah is not אסור assur to a
normal כהן, kohen, but a ספק חליצה safek chalitza is. Okay, yeah.
Is it, I just want to be clarified something basic.
So קידושין שאינו ראוי לביאה Kiddushin she-eino ra-uy l'viah is always a
case of like total ספק. safek. Right, well you didn't know from
the outset, right. Right. It's the moment the קידושין Kiddushin is חל,
chal, it was never able to be to be consummated. Okay, so
חליצה מן האירוסין chalitza min ha-erusin is not אסור assur to a
כהן. kohen. Yes she is. But if she would have gotten חליצה,
chalitza, would she have been אסור assur to a כהן? kohen? No,
she'd be an אלמנה. almanah. So then aren't we now making a
problem and making her a פסולה לכהן? pesulah le-kohen? Yes. What are
you supposed to do though? Okay, no, so I'm asking. Yeah. All
right, so גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. תא שמע. Ta shma.
Come hear. דתני תיביומי. de-tani Tiviumi. תיביומי Tiviumi taught. לזה חמישה בנים,
lezeh chamishah banim, חמישה, chamishah, excuse me, ולזה חמישה בנות. u-lezeh chamishah
banot. This guy has five daughters, this guy has five sons. Five
sons and five daughters. ואמר אחת מבנותיך מקודשת לאחד מבני. v'amar achas
mibnotekha mekudeshet l'achad mibanai. And and and he says, listen, my sons
want me to marry a woman for them. Let's marry one of
your daughters to one of my sons. Okay. כל אחת ואחת צריכה
חמישה גיטין. kol achas ve-achas tzrichah chamishah gittin. So I don't know
which son I married it to, you don't know which daughter you
married it to to me to my son. So each one of
your daughters needs five גיטין gittin from all of my sons, okay,
because any one of your daughters might be married to any one
of my sons. So each each daughter needs five גיטין. gittin. This
is the author of all these משניות, mishnayot, by the way, right?
Yes, was הושעיה. Osaya. Right, okay. מת אחד מהם. meis achad meihem.
But the statement has to be more specific. Is it that they
forgot which one? Well no, that's exactly what we're being מדייק, medayek,
that the statement is, for the we finally actually have the quote
marks of the statement. אחת מבנותיך לאחד מבני. achas mibnotekha l'achad mibanai.
One of your daughters is married to one of my sons. So
that proves that we never knew. But that's precisely... Well that's exactly
the point, you see it is, even if they're non-specific it's effective.
Okay. So so the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
next. מת אחד מהם, meis achad meihem, if one of the sons
died, so כל אחת ואחת צריכה ארבעה גיטין וחליצה מאחד מהם. kol
achas ve-achas tzrichah arba'ah gittin ve-chalitza mei'achad meihem. Okay, each one of
them needs four גיטין gittin from the surviving but only one חליצה,
chalitza, right, because if you get one חליצה chalitza from one brother
you're okay. So each girl, woman, whatever, girl, needs four גיטין gittin
because she might be married to brothers two through through five.
So from two through five she needs a גט. get. Because she
might have been married to dead brother number one, she's going to
need a חליצה, chalitza, but she doesn't need a חליצה chalitza from
all four of the guys, she only needs one of them, well
any one brother can do a חליצה chalitza to her. So every
girl needs four גיטין gittin and one חליצה. chalitza. Okay. What? Why
four? Oh, she needs...
from one guy she needs both a גט get and a חליצה.
chalitza. Right. One guy will give her a has to give her
a גט get because it might be his wife, and one of
them will also give a חליצה chalitza because it could be his
brother's wife.
Is that clear? Okay. The fifth guy would have... the first guy
would have given a גט get but he's dead. Okay. So צריכה
ארבעה גיטין וחליצה מאחד מהם. tzrichah arba'ah gittin ve-chalitza mei'achad meihem. וכי
תימא הכא נמי כשהוכר ולסוף נתערבו? ve-chi teima hakha nami kshehukkar ve-sof
nisarev?
Now
maybe you'll say this is also a case where we initially knew
who was married to whom and then we completely forgot. הא, ha,
but here we have quote marks about what was said. אחת מבנותיך
לאחד מבני. achas mibnotekha l'achad mibanai. One of your daughters to one
of my sons, it sounds like it's non-specific from the outset. קתני,
katanei, and it seems that even if it's non-specific from the outset,
it works and it's חל מספק chal misafek and you just don't
know which one. And therefore, okay, you see,
I mean A you sort of see what is a חידוש chiddush
in itself, that you can marry somebody, you know, to be you
know in an unspecified way. For that's קידושין שאינו ראוי לביאה. Kiddushin
she-eino ra-uy l'viah. You might think that if you don't know if
you haven't identified the person you're married, like something substantively missing from
the transaction. Okay, but somehow we're not saying that. So it can
be non-specified and it can be married to any one of them
מספק, misafek, even though, right, I mean forget sisters. Let's say I
said, here, take this money and I'll be married to one of
the three of you, you three you know women that are standing
there. Take it and I'll and whatever. So you could say like
how could you be how could a קידושין Kiddushin happen if it's
to a non-specified person. But somehow that we accept and not only
that, even if it's because that they're sisters and it won't allow
for a sex to happen with any one of them and it's
never ראוי לביאה, ra-uy l'viah, it still works. So it's a proof
like אביי, Abaye, okay, cause that's exactly the case. So the גמרא
Gemara says תיובתא דרבא תיובתא, tiyuvta de-Rava tiyuvta, fine, that although everything
else was stacking up against רבא, Rava, this absolutely proves that רבא
Rava is
wrong. And והלכתא כוותיה דאביי ביע"ל קג"ם, hilchasa k'vosei d'Abaye b'Yal K'gam,
and even though we always
פוסקין poskin like רבא, Rava, there are six cases we פוסק pasken
like אביי, Abaye, the acronym is יע"ל קג"ם Yal K'gam and this
is the ק Kuf קידושין שאינה מסורה לביאה. Kiddushin she'eina mesura liviah.
We'll talk about the others in a minute. Dov, you had a
question. This works very well against the father of the daughters because
he has the right to marry off his daughters to who he
chooses, but the father of the son, I mean that's all tied
up in שליחות, shlichus, what kind of שליחות shlichus is that? You'd
have to say that each one made him a שליח. shliach. Dad,
whichever girl you pick for me, I'm fine with it, you decide.
So let's talk about the acronym. So י Yud is there's some
debate about what some of them stand for, but the general assumption
is י Yud is יאוש שלא מדעת, yeiush she'lo m'da'as, which the
second פרק perek of if somebody is מיאש m'yaiesh on something without
really, like had they known they would have been מיאש m'yaiesh but
they didn't know, is that considered יאוש? yeiush? Okay, ע Ayin is
עד זומם eid zomem whether למפרע הוא נפסל. le'mafrea hu nifsal. If
somebody becomes an עד זומם, eid zomem, then retroactively he's a פסול
לעדות pasul l'eidus from the time he gave his עדות eidus not
from the time that the witnesses testify against him in court. ל
Lamed is לחי העומד מאליו, lechi ha'omed mei'elav, although there's some debate
about what the ל Lamed is. ק Kuf is קידושין שאינה מסורה
לביאה. Kiddushin she'eina mesura liviah. ג Gimmel is oh, ג Gimmel is
גילוי דעת בגיט. gilluy da'as b'get. You might remember that from when
we did גיטין Gittin where it's a little like about whatever, about
דברים שבלב, devarim she'belev, like somebody says something, oy, you know, I
wish you would have done this, do we interpret certain things as
an indication of what he's thinking and to be effective even if
he didn't actually say something, גילוי דעת בגיט. gilluy da'as b'get. And
מ Mem is what's מ? Mem? מ Mem is מומר אוכל נבילות
לתיאבון. mumar ochel neveilos l'tei'avon. If somebody is a מומר mumar not
להכעיס, l'hach'is, but somebody who has a יצר הרע yeitzer hara and
is constantly עובר over on a particular עבירה, aveirah, does that make
him פסול לעדות pasul l'eidus or not? That's the way רש"י Rashi
has the list, תוספות Tosafos has a slightly different list. Yes. So
just getting back to this, because like you know, we had this
case of someone who משלח שליח לקדש אחת מן השוק m'shalach shliach
l'kadesh achas min hashuk and he doesn't know, so he's like אסור
assur for like anyone who has like a sister, you know, them
or because whatever, right? But we don't see that the women are
all אסורות, assuros, right? But here we sort of are making a
problem for the women, or are we not? Or are we just
doing it vis-à-vis the men? When should we say women are all
אסורות? assuros? What do you say? Don't say that. Here we do?
If someone said, if someone sent a שליח shliach
to מקדש mekadesh that's different, that's a whole thing. תוספות Tosafos says
I mean it's crazy that we're so מחמיר machmir for that. תוספות
Tosafos says it's a קנס knas on the guy. And anyway, the
women would know he accepted the קידושין, Kiddushin, so that problem we
can't here's a case where a particular set of women and a
particular set of men are בספק. b'safek. In that case, you know,
there's no particular set of women that are בספק. b'safek. The women
are saying that yes, it could be, or whatever it is in
this case. I mean whatever, this is a case, yeah, where clearly
there are identified women who are בספק. b'safek. That's an unrelated case.
That's a case where you have no idea who the women were
who were involved. Yeah. תיובתא דרבא תיובתא. tiyufta d'Rava tiyufta. So in
ש"ס Shas in general, when they say that formulation תיובתא דפלוני תיובתא,
tiyufta d'peloni tiyufta, does it most of the time mean like it
means here, or is it most of the time mean no, his
position stands, because it could mean both? No, no, no. תיובתא דאיקס
תיובתא tiyufta d'X tiyufta is almost always a complete rejection and we
פוסק pasken the other way. Every now and then the גמרא Gemara
says תיובתא דאיקס והלכתא כאיקס. tiyufta d'X v'hilchasa k'X. And then the
גמרא Gemara says תיובתא והלכתא? tiyufta v'hilchasa? How could you? But when
it says תיובתא דרבא תיובתא, tiyufta d'Rava tiyufta, it's almost always complete
rejection. Now by the way, for those that are interested in this
type of stuff, at the end of תוספות ביע"ל קג"ם, Tosafos b'Yal
K'gam, תוספות Tosafos says like this, and he says like this: because
תוספות Tosafos has a question which one of the יע"ל קג"ם Yal
K'gams were, so he said why don't we include some other cases
where we פוסק pasken like אביי, Abaye, like a case about תחילתו
בפשיעה וסופו באונס, techilaso b'fshia v'sofo b'ones, why we פוסק pasken like
אביי Abaye against רבא, Rava, why isn't that included in this acronym?
So if you look at the end of תוספות ביע"ל קג"ם, Tosafos
b'Yal K'gam, he says וספרים לא כתבו v'sefarim lo chasvu it's about
five lines before the תוספות Tosafos is over where the word says
כתבו, chasvu, וספרים לא כתבו והלכתא בהך שמעתתא. v'sefarim lo chasvu v'hilchasa
b'hach shema'teta. Over there in that case about תחילתו בפשיעה, techilaso b'fshia,
it doesn't say והלכתא כאביי. v'hilchasa k'Abaye. אבל כתב בהלכות גדולות. aval
kasav b'Halachos Gedolos. והכי כתב בספרים גבי המפקיד מעות אצל חבירו ובעובדא
דציפתא דאורבני. v'hachi kasav b'sefarim gabei hamaphkid ma'os etzel chaveiro u've'uvda d'tzifta
d'orbnei. ונראה לפרש דלהכי לא נכתבה בכלל יע"ל קג"ם, v'nir'eh l'fareish d'lahachi
lo nechtava b'chlal Yal K'gam, ודלאחר כך נפסקה הך הלכתא כרבנן סבוראי,
u'd'le'achar kach nipsaka hach hilchasa k'Rabbanan Savorai, because some of the הלכתאs
hilchasa in the גמרא Gemara were not in the initial גמרא. Gemara.
So were actually introduced in the post-גמרא Gemara editing by the רבנן
סבוראי Rabbanan Savorai or maybe they were introduced in the הלכות גדולות.
Halachos Gedolos. Sometime some of the הלכתאs hilchasa appear how the הלכות
גדולות Halachos Gedolos פוסקs, pasken but because it's all in Aramaic, he
quotes the גמרא Gemara and then he adds on his own הלכתא
כפלוני, hilchasa k'peloni, but it sounds like it's the גמרא. Gemara. So
sometimes what the הלכות גדולות Halachos Gedolos added, the הלכתא, hilchasa, got
then put back into the גמרא Gemara because people thought that was
part of the initial text of the גמרא. Gemara. So sometimes the
הלכתאs hilchasa in the גמרא. Gemara. are actually post the סיום הש"ס,
Siyum HaShas, and תוספות Tosafos says, and you see because there are
some הלכתות Hilchosas like אביי Abaye which are not included in the
יעל קג"ם. Yal K'Gam. So it's interesting to note that sometimes what's
in our text includes glosses of the רבנן סבוראי Rabbanan Savorai which
are after the חתימת הש"ס Chasimas HaShas or the גאונים Geonim etc.
The gloss of פשיטות הגאונים Pshitos HaGeonim is a later פסק psak
like אביי. Abaye. Okay, מעשה maise back to the גמרא. Gemara. מעשה
בחמישה נשים. Maise b'chamisha nashim. Now we deal with that case about
the five women that he took, he picked this basket of figs
and he married them. There were two sisters among them, which is
how we got into the whole issue of קידושין שאינו מסור לביאה.
Kiddushin she-eino masur l'biah. And he said all of you are married
to me. Now the story about those and it says that the
sisters aren't married. Fine. But all of those figs, they were not
his figs, they were their figs. But it was שמיטה, Shmita, it
was a שביעית Shviis year. So that created a קידושין. Kiddushin. Let's
take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רב: Amar
Rav: שמע מינה ממתניתין ארבע. Shma mina mimatnisin arba. Our משנה Mishnah
is teaching us four הלכות. Halachos. ונקט רב בידו תלת, Venakad Rav
b'yadei tlas, but I only know the פסק psak of it by
three because I don't know how to interpret the משנה Mishnah regarding
the fourth הלכה. Halacha. Did he speak in the third person? Well,
yeah, okay, I guess. שמע מינה המקדש בפירות שביעית מקודשת, Shma mina
hamikadesh b'peiros shviis mekudeshes, that if you use the fruit of שמיטה,
Shmita, you can marry somebody with it. Now what's the חידוש? chidush?
I mean, you know, if you're able to take it for yourself,
you take it. It's הפקר hefker fruit and then you marry somebody
with it. So, רש"י Rashi does suppose what the חידוש chidush is
is that what you're supposed to do it says והיתה שבת הארץ
לכם לאכלה, v'haysa shabbas ha'aretz lachem l'ochla, you're supposed to eat it,
you're not supposed to do סחורה, s'chor, you're not supposed to do
business. So maybe if I used it in a type of a
transactional way, maybe the קידושין Kiddushin would not be חל. chal. קא
משמע לן Kamashmalan that even though I wasn't supposed to, if I
use it in a transaction, the transaction still takes effect. And that
the קידושין Kiddushin is not like סחורה s'chor now. Well, that could
be also, but even if it were, if I buy stuff with
פירות שביעית, peiros shviis, it's still that the transaction works even though
I wasn't supposed to. So that's number one. ושמע מינה קידשה בגזל
אינה מקודשת. Ushma mina Kiddusha b'gezel eina mekudeshes. If it was just
normally stolen goods, because basically he picked their figs and gave it
back to them. So the only reason it worked was because it
was שמיטה Shmita because it was הפקר hefker and he was allowed
to pick their figs. But if it hadn't been שמיטה Shmita it
wouldn't work. So if you marry somebody with stuff you stole from
them, אינה מקודשת. eina mekudeshes. אפילו בגזל דידה. Afillu b'gezel didah. But
even if it's stuff you stole from her. Now you could say
that's even more offensive. Of course it's not מקודשת, mekudeshes, he gave
it back to me and I'm just taking back my own thing,
I'm not marrying him. But you could also say well the fact
that I said yes, I would marry him when he gave me
back the apple that he stole off of my stand, well you
could say לכאורה l'chura that it's even less מקודשת mekudeshes because you
just wanted your apple back. But you could say the fact that
I agreed to meant I was מחל mochel the apple to him,
let him keep the apple so he could use it for כסף
קידושין kesef kiddushin because I said I would agree to be married
with him by it. But no, we wouldn't say that. And it's
only because it's שמיטה Shmita that it works. No reason she'd want
to be married. One minute. ממאי מדקתני של עמה היתה, Mimai midekani
shel am haisa, it was their figs, ושם שביעית היתה, v'shom shviis
haisa, but it was שמיטה. Shmita. טעמא דשביעית כהפקר הוא, Tama d'shviis
k'hefker hu, the reason was שמיטה Shmita was הפקר hefker and therefore
it became his. הא דשאר שני שבוע, Had'shaar shatei hashuva, if it
had been another year during the שמיטה Shmita cycle, לא, lo, it
wouldn't have worked even though, and we would not say that by
giving her back her own thing she's implicitly saying it's okay you
can keep it and use it to marry me with it. So
that's point number two. ושמע מינה point number three is אשה נעשית
שליח shliach לחברתה, a woman could represent her friend to be accept
כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. אפילו במקום שנעשית לה צרה, Afillu b'makom shenasis
lah tzara, even when she becomes a competitor wife. Because remember he
wanted to marry all five of the women, and it worked, one
of them was able to represent the group minus the sisters, even
though I was accepting כסף קידושין kesef kiddushin for myself and for
a woman who would be my co-wife. And we might have said
in that case maybe like, maybe if I explicitly said I'm her
שליח shliach. fine. But in this case I didn't explicitly say I'm
her שליח. shliach The guy gave it to me and says take
this so I can be married to all of you. Maybe we'll
say in that case implicitly I never, even though I was silent,
I never agreed to represent those other women. Who wants to have
a co-wife, right? So you might think that in that case certainly
in a case of a silence maybe she should not be seen
as the שליח of those other women since she's getting married herself
to this guy. קא משמע לן Kamashmalan she is. Those three things
we hear from this משנה. Mishnah. Okay, ואידך, v'idach, and what's the
fourth thing that the משנה Mishnah is teaching but we're not so
what the משנה Mishnah is teaching? מאי היא? Mai hi? קידושין שאינו
מסור לביאה. Kiddushin she-eino masur l'biah. It's teaching you something about קידושין
שאינו מסור לביאה. Kiddushin she-eino masur l'biah. Okay, because there's two sisters
here and they're not married. The question is ונחשביה, v'nichshvei, so then
say that it's telling me the פסק psak about קידושין שאינו מסור
לביאה. Kiddushin she-eino masur l'biah. No. משום דמספקא ליה אי כאביי אי
כרבא. Mishum d'mesafkeilei i k'Abaye i k'Rava. Because we didn't know which
way it's paskening about that. If you remember the other day, we
didn't know how to interpret the case of the two sisters. Was
he saying I'm marrying one of the two sisters? And then it
doesn't work and then it's like אביי? Abaye? And then it's like
רבא? Rava? קידושין שאינו מסור לביאה Kiddushin she-eino masur l'biah doesn't work.
Even if I just tried to marry one of them, right? Or
is it telling me that I'm trying to marry both sisters, and
the reason it doesn't work is because I can't be married to
both? But if I was only trying to marry one of them,
it would have worked. So because we don't know how to read
the משנה mishna *Mishna* when I'm trying to marry these five women,
if I'm trying to marry both of the sisters or one of
them, I don't know what it's telling me about קידושין kiddushin שאינן
מסורות לביאה *kiddushin she'eino mesuran l'biah*. קידושין kiddushin? שאינן מסורות לביאה *kiddushin
she'eino mesuran l'biah* is only the scenario where I'm trying to marry
one of them. If that was the case of the משנה mishna
*Mishna*, then it's telling me that קידושין שאינן מסורות לביאה *kiddushin she'eino
mesuran l'biah* doesn't work. But if the משנה mishna *Mishna*'s scenario is
that I'm trying to marry both the sisters, then it's telling me
that a normal case of קידושין שאינן מסורות לביאה *kiddushin she'eino mesuran
l'biah* would work. So I can't figure out, the משנה mishna *Mishna*
clearly has a position about קידושין שאינן מסורות לביאה *kiddushin she'eino mesuran
l'biah*, I just don't know what that position is because I don't
know whether the case is both sisters or one of the sisters.
Okay, anyway, moving on. We're not going to belabor the קידושין שאינן
מסורות לביאה *kiddushin she'eino mesuran l'biah*. Back to the basic issue here
about שמיטה shmita *shmita* and the whole thing. כי סליק רבי זירא
*Ki salk Rebbe Zeira*, when רבי זירא *Rebbe Zeira* went up to
ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisroel*, אמר amar, לה האי שמעתא קמיה דרבי יוחנן
*amar lah hai shmaita kamey d'Rebbe Yochanan* and he told over this
discussion, this thing to רבי יוחנן *Rebbe Yochanan* about, you know, what
רבא Rava *Rava* inferred from the whole משנה Mishna. *Mishna* or רב
*Rav* inferred from the whole משנה *Mishna*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says אמר ליה Amar lei, מי אמר רב הכי *amar lei mi
amar Rav haki*? Did רב *Rav* really say this? And we'll see
in a minute what he was astounded by was the position that
you can't marry with a stolen object. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, what do you mean? Why are you so astounded? והוא לא
אמר *vehu lo amar*? Are you רבי יוחנן *Rebbe Yochanan*, don't you
agree to this? ואמר רבי יוחנן גזל gezel ולא נתייאשו הבעלים *v'amar
Rebbe Yochanan gazel velo niyashu hab'alim*, if you steal something and there's
yet to be יאוש yeiush, *yei'ush*, the owners have yet to give
up hope of getting it back, then שניהם אינם יכולים להקדיש *shneihem
einam yecholim l'hakdish*, you can't, neither the owner nor the גנב *gannav*
can sanctify the object. This is talking about sanctifying, not marrying a
woman. זה לפי שאינו שלו *zeh l'fi she'eino shelo*, the גנב *gannav*
can't because it's not his, obviously he can't sanctify it. וזה לפי
שאינה ברשותו *v'zeh l'fi she'eino birshuso*, and the owners can't because even
though the owner owns the object, it's no longer under his control.
And if it's no longer under his control, you're not allowed to
do anything with it. You lose a certain degree of control and
mastery and rights over it when it's not under your control. The
גנב *gannav* kind of does own it. Wouldn't it be like sort
of בריך *barech*? Alright, that might be, but we're not going to
worry about it. So the חידוש chiddush *chiddush* of רבי יוחנן *Rebbe
Yochanan* really is less that the גנב *gannav* can't be מקדיש *makdish*
it, of course he can't be מקדיש *makdish* it, it's not yours.
His חידוש *chiddush* is more that the owner can't be מקדיש *makdish*
it because it's not, even though the owner owns it, it's not
under his control. But nevertheless, everybody agrees that you can't do something
with an object you don't own. You can't be מקדיש *makdish* it,
you can't use it to marry a woman. So why is רבי
יוחנן *Rebbe Yochanan* so surprised that that's what רב *Rav* learned from
the משנה *Mishna*? It should be a pretty patently obvious point that
you can't marry somebody with stolen goods. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, no, הכי קאמר ליה *hachi ka amar lei*. He wasn't astounded,
or he didn't disagree with what רב *Rav* said, here's what he
was saying: מי אמר רב כוותי *mi amar Rav kvasai*? Oh, I
didn't realize that רב *Rav* said the same thing I did. I
feel so good! Now we're, you know, we both say the same
פסק *psak*. Again, the surprising thing is, and why is that a
חידוש *chiddush*? Like this all should be so patently obvious, right, that
you can't marry somebody with stolen goods? Anyway, the גמרא gemara *Gemara*
continues. מתיבי *Meisivei*, because now we're going to see a case where
maybe you can marry somebody with something stolen. קידשה בגזל *Kidsha b'gazel*,
if you married a woman with a stolen object, בחמס ובגניבה *b'chamas
u'vigniva* or money that was חמס *chamas*, sort of like maybe extorted,
thank you, that's a perfect word, or something that was burgled. Okay.
או שחטף סלע מידה וקידשה *o shechataph sela miyada v'kidsha*, or you
took a coin from her hand and gave it back to her,
מקודשת *mekudeshes*, it works. So it's not so obvious. It looks like
you can marry somebody with stolen goods, which is shocking. Now again,
maybe some of this, well let's see what the גמרא *Gemara* says.
התם בגזל דידה *Hasam b'gazel deeda*, no, there it works because you're
giving her back her own object. So the fact that she's agreeing
to accept it means that she's being מוחל mochel *mochel* it to
you and that it actually, you know, it does work, because now
she's somehow giving it to you to give to her. So the
גמרא *Gemara* says, one minute, הא מדקתני סיפא *ha mi ditni seifa*,
the end of that teaches, או שחטף סלע משלה *o shechataph sela
mishela*, the end of that teaching, or you stole a coin out
of her hand. So the end of it was you were using
money you stole from her. מכלל דרישא *miklal d'reisha*, the beginning, which
was more generic, was בגזל דעלמא *b'gazel d'alma* עסקינן *askinnin*. So first
of all, that's not true. That seems clear from that source that
it's סתם *stam* stolen goods you can be מקדש *mekadesh* her with.
גמרא *Gemara* says no, פרושי קא מפרש *perushei ka mefareish*. No no,
the end of the משנה *Mishna* of that ברייתא braita *braisa* is
explaining the beginning. קידשה בגזל בחמס ובגניבה *kidsha b'gazel b'chamas u'vigniva*, if
you married her with stolen goods, כיצד *keitzad*, what type of stolen
goods are we talking about? כגון שחטף סלע מידה וקידשה בו *kegon
shechataph sela miyada v'kidsha bo*, like you stole goods from her hand,
meaning from things you stole from her. Normal stolen goods would not
work, but if you married her with things you stole from her.
That would work. Okay, now, wait, I've got a couple things. First
of all, A, shouldn't we say she's just trying to get her
סלע back? And B, what about the point that we made that
our משנה about the figs proves that if it weren't שמיטה shmita
you couldn't marry her with her own stolen goods you stole from
her. So that's the next thing now the גמרא asks. והא מתניתין
דגזל דידה, Ve-ha matnitin de-gezel dida, our משנה the figs, you're taking
something that was hers, וקתני רב אינה מקודשת ve-katni Rav eina mekudeshet
and we said the whole point of the משנה is that if
it wasn't שמיטה you wouldn't be married because you're giving her back
because you know even though it was stuff you stole from her.
So how can this other this ברייתא braita say you are married?
לא קשיא, Lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא דשדיך והא דלא שדיך.
Ha de-shadikh ve-ha de-la shadikh. The question was, was there an engagement
beforehand or not? Oh my god. So if you're doing it in
a vacuum and you're taking something from her and she's saying הרי
את מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshet li and she says give it
to me and she takes it, we'll say she's not מוחלת, mochelet,
she's trying to get her object back. But if it's not coming
in a vacuum, if you've already had been through an engagement process
and she agreed to marry you and you're engaged and then you
stole from her and gave it back then in that context we'll
interpret it as oh she's just מוחלת. mochelet. Okay, not a great
way to enter into a marriage, the husband's already stealing from you.
Under the חופה, chuppah, under the חופה, chuppah, the מסדר קידושין mesader
kiddushin calls up the עדים eidim and the חתן chatan says honey
give me the ring that's on your finger for a minute. No,
or he says give it's easier, חתן chatan just he takes it
from her. They're already seeing it like joint property, I see, ah
that's stealing, we're already like we're married, we're rom-com. Okay fine then.
Alright, anyway, so that's how we've resolved it. But you do see
why it was a little bit of a חידוש that you can't
marry with גזל gezel though logically of course you shouldn't be able
to marry with גזל gezel but there was this ברייתא braita that
sounds like you can. So we had to find a way to
like tame that ברייתא braita. and you know and sort of contextualize
it and say we're only talking about a case of גזל דידה
gezel dida and only a case where there had been already שידוכין
shidduchim and an engagement and only then could that possibly work. Jay,
did you have another question? Yeah, just a back question. Now this
is קידושין we're talking about? Right. And now we're establishing a process
that precedes קידושין? Yeah. Well the גמרא's talked about that before about
שידוכין, shidduchim, not that it has הלכה halakha bindingness but that it
creates a context to allow us to interpret other things. Okay, but
it's not הלכה halakha bindingly but yes but I mean that came
up the שידוכין shidduchim came up before I think in I'm trying
to remember where but we had it very recently as well yeah.
So is this only if she said that for something like this
that she's okay with it? Not okay but she said okay you
know she accepted it. Right because we were talking about other things
oh because of course some people wouldn't want to be married to
people in some cases. Yeah yeah yeah but she's the one who
said okay yeah I mean if she wouldn't say okay she wouldn't
have agreed. What if we found out later that like you know
he stole it from her and she found out later. Ah right
then we said it might have been that's a good point sham-presumably
right that's a good point. Okay, so the גמרא says like this.
Okay. ההיא איתתא, Hahi iteta, a certain woman דהוה קמשכרא במשיכלא, de-hava
kamash-chakre be-mashichala, she was washing her feet in a basin דמיא de-maya
in a whatever basin of water. What seems to be completely irrelevant
to the story as you'll see. אתו גברא, Atu gavra, a certain
man came חטף זוזי מחבריה, chataf zuzei mi-chaveirei, he swiped a coin
out of his friend's hand ושדא לה v'shada lah and threw it
to her. אמר לה מקדשת לי, Amar lah mekudeshet li, be married
to me. Okay, so maybe it's relevant that she was washing her
feet that she didn't have the time to throw it back at
him or to say anything anyway. But now it's גזל of some
other person. Okay. אתו גברא לקמיה דרבא, Atu gavra le-kamei de-Rava, so
this man came to רבא and said basically am I married to
this woman? אמר ליה, amar lei he says, לית דחש לה להא
דרבי שמעון, leis de-chash lah le-ha de-Rebbi Shimon, nobody is concerned with
רבי שמעון's Rebbi Shimon position which occurs in a משנה in כלים
Keilim that says that when you steal something, גזילה, gezeila, it's like
robbery, you know it's like meaning so so you see the thief.
Okay, and there's a whole discussion where am I more likely to
give up hope of ever getting something back if I'm burgled if
it's a case of burglary, גניבה, gneiva, as such that I don't
know the people, I'll never find them, I'll never get it back
or no maybe you could say you know they're
cowards they do it in hiding so maybe if I do find
them we'll be able to get the money back or גזילה gezeila
do you say גזילה gezeila is I know the people so therefore
it'll be easier for me to get it back I'm not מייאש
meyayesh or do you say the opposite I know them and they
had the חוצפה chutzpah and the brazenness to steal it even in
broad daylight oh that's it I'm never going to find anyway so
there's a question whether you say סתם גניבה stam gneiva is יאוש
בעלים ye'ush ba'alim or סתם גזילה stam gezeila is יאוש בעלים. ye'ush
ba'alim. So since he is saying this is a case of גזילה
gezeila it was in broad daylight so if we would assume that
the original guy that the owner of this money was מייאש meyayesh
so maybe it could be a case of and this actually would
be an interesting discussion of whether you can be מקדש בגזל mekadesh
be-gezel now we're getting to see where why this would be a
possibility because it could be a case of יאוש ושינוי רשות. ye'ush
v'shinui reshuyot. I swiped the money from Michael, he's מייאש, meyayesh, he
doesn't think he's ever going to get it back, I go to
a woman and say הרי את מקודשת לי בטבעת זו harei at
mekudeshet li be-tabaat zu which I just stole off. of Michael and
now it's יאוש, yeiush, excuse me יאש, ya'ash, and it's שינוי רשות.
shinui reshus. She owns it. She doesn't have to give it back.
I might have to pay Michael because I stole it from him,
but she doesn't have to give the ring back because it was
יאוש ושינוי רשות, yeiush v'shinui reshus, right? So everybody see how that
mechanics can work? Right? So in that case, maybe I can be
מקדש בגזל. mekadesh b'gezel. I still have to pay you back, but
she gets but I gave her something that okay, it wasn't mine
when I gave it to her, but the act of me giving
it to her allowed her to take possession of it. So maybe
that's enough of being מקדש בכסף. mekadesh b'kesef. So that now we're
beginning to see why קידושי גזל kiddushei gezel could work. But his
answer was, now we're not concerned not קידושי גזל kiddushei gezel couldn't
work if there was יאוש, yeiush maybe if there was יאוש yeiush.
it could, but we're not concerned that there was יאוש. yeiush ליכא
דחש להדרבי שמעון, leika d'chash l'had'rabbi shimon, nobody's concerned for Rabbi Shimon
דאמר סתם גזילה יאוש בעלים, d'amar stam gezeila yeiush be'alim, that we
should presume that there was יאוש here. Okay, הפי. hafi. Now, ההוא
אריסא, hahu arisa, there was a sharecropper דקדש במוזא דשמכי דסמכי d'kadesh
b'muza d'shamchi d'samchi I guess with he he married with a bundle
of רש״י Rashi says like a a handful of of onions I
think, what does רש״י Rashi say? Yeah, a handful of onions. Okay,
אתא לקמיה דרבא. ata l'kamei d'rava. Now of course these onions were
from the owner of the field. He was the sharecropper. It wasn't
his onions. Okay, so אמר ליה amar lei מאן אחלה לך, man
achlah lach, who was מוחל mochel to you? Okay, those weren't yours
yet to give. Yes, you will eventually get a percentage of the
crops, but those weren't yours yet to give. And you work you
pay a percentage and well after you have all the crops, you
divide them and before this was before the crops were divided. Exactly.
אתא לקמיה דרבא ata l'kamei d'rava came to Rava, אמר ליה amar
lei מאן אחלה לך, man achlah lach, who was מוחל to you?
Those weren't yours yet to give. והני מילי במוזא, v'hanei milei b'muza,
that's only if you did it with just like you took like
a hand-breath. אבל כישא, aval kisha, if they had been bundled, if
you'd already made them into bundles of onions, okay, and so you
know you so then מצי אמר ליה, matzi amar lei, you can
say to the owner of the field, אנא שקילנא כישא, ana shakilna
kisha, I'll take one bundle, שקול את כישא, shakul at kisha, you
take another bundle, כישא כי כישא, kisha ki kisha, bundle for bundle.
Meaning if there's a general understanding that you split the crop 50/50,
okay, so if you're just grabbing
like a random like okay, you're going to split it 50/50, that
doesn't entitle you to start eating apples off the tree. When you
divide it, you divide it. You get your part. Okay, but if
stuff has already been bundled up and you took one bundle, you
could say I'm taking one bundle and that'll be towards my credit
and then you know you'll you know and you'll and you'll get
an extra bundle when it comes time to divide. That's seen as
already like a you're allowed to begin the division at that stage.
But like a regular worker in your field I can, right? Because
I'm allowed to eat some? Yeah, but that's only if you're eating
as you're doing it, not to go take to be מקדש אישה.
mekadesh isha. Okay, but that's interesting, right? So if you have this
understanding that you divide 50/50, at what stage are you allowed to
do a little impromptu mini division? I'm just going to take this
on credit of the stuff that's owed to me. So it says
if it's already bundled up then you can start already dividing and
say I'll take one bundle, you'll take another one, but to just
take a handful of it, that's stealing, that's not yet taking your
portion. It could be 70/30? It could be 70/30, whatever it could
be. Exactly, exactly. It could be 70/30, whatever the number is. But
it has to be in a way that it's seen as dividing
up the assets and not just taking. Okay, so the גמרא says
like this. ההוא סרסיא, hahu sarsiya, excuse me סרסיא, sarsaya, דקדש בפורמא
דשיכרא. d'kadesh b'purma d'shichra. So a certain person who basically was a
beer maker, okay, and he and he basically be a similar thing,
people would give him the beer the you know the the dates
he would make beer out of dates or mead, people would give
it to him and he would and he would make it into
beer and he would get part and he would get part of
the profit. Okay, and he married a woman with a vessel that
would you know be used for storing this beer, which wasn't his
vessel, which was the owner's vessel. אתא מרי דשיכרא ata marei d'shichra
and the owner of the beer came, אשכחיה ashkachei and found him,
אמר ליה אמאי לא יהבת מהאי חריפא, amai lo yahavat mehai charifa,
why did you give from that vessel? You should have given it
from a from a vessel that was more pungent, apparently the vessels
had like you know absorbed a lot of the taste of the
beer in them, so give her from a better vessel that had
absorbed more of the taste of the beer. Now, was he being
was he being serious or was he being sarcastic? Okay, because it
was his vessel that was being given. So אתא לקמיה דרבא, ata
l'kamei d'rava, they came to Rava. אמר, he said, לא אמרו כלך
אצל יפות, lo amru k'lach etzel yafot, this idea we have in
a similar case where somebody said "Oh, you should have given the
better one, you should have gone to the better ones," אלא בתרומה
בלבד, ela bitruma bilvad, that's only by תרומה, truma, because by תרומה
truma I have to take תרומה truma from my grain. So if
you did it on your own and I say certain things that
might signal that I'm okay with it, but in this case, nobody
entitled you to take my vessels and marry a woman with them.
What's the case by תרומה? truma? דתניא, d'tanya, we learned a ברייתא.
כיצד אמרו התורם שלא מדעת תרומתו תרומה, keitzad amru hatorim shelo midaat
trumato truma, what would be the case that if you took תרומה
truma without the owner's consent, it would still work? Because normally you
need שליחות. shlichut. הרי שירד לתוך שדה חבירו, harei sheyarad l'toch s'deh
chaveiro,
he went into his friend's field, וליקט v'likat and he gathered the
fruit, ותרם שלא ברשות v'taram shelo birshut and he took תרומה truma
without permission. אם חושש משום גזל, im choshesh mishum gezel, if the
owner basically... consider it to be like you're basically stealing from him,
you know, אין תרומתו תרומה, ein Trumaso Truma, it's not. ואם לאו
תרומתו תרומה, V'im lav Trumaso Truma, if not, it is. Which means,
when does it work? When he's not upset, when he's okay with
it. So how do you know if he's okay with it? So
ומנין ומנין, u'minayin u'minayin, how do you know אם חושש משום גזל
אם לאו? im choshesh mishum gezel im lav? How do you know
if he considers it like you're stealing from him? How do you
know if he's okay with it or not? הרי שבא בעל הבית
ומצאו, Harei sheba baal habayis u'metzao, there you were, you were on
your own going to my field, harvesting and taking תרומה, Truma, and
I came and I found what you were doing, and I said
to him, ואמר לו, v'amar lo, כלך אצל יפות, Klach etzel yafos,
you know, why'd you only take תרומה Truma from their grain? You
should've taken the תרומה Truma from the better grain. So now let's
see. אם נמצאו יפות מהם, Im nimtze'u yafos mehem, if there really
is better grain, תרומתו תרומה, Trumaso Truma, it's good, so then we
assume what I'm saying is serious, not sarcastic. And therefore, it's indicating
that I'm okay with what you did. Oh, very nice, you should've
even used the better stuff. ואם לאו, V'im lav, but if there's
nothing better, and I'm saying, oh, you should've done even the better
stuff, then אין תרומתו תרומה, ein Trumaso Truma, what I'm really doing
is a way of saying, like, I can't believe you used my
best grain for תרומה, Truma, and I'm clearly expressing my displeasure. Okay,
now, היו הבעלים מלקטים ומוסיפים, Hayu habaalim melaktim u'mosifim,
if, however, you were doing it and then I joined in with
you and started picking with you and participating with you, בין כך
ובין כך תרומתו תרומה, bein kach u'vein kach Trumaso Truma, either way
it works. Anyway, that's by תרומה. Truma. By תרומה, Truma, obviously, I
have to take תרומה Truma anyway. So if I'll use, if I
say something, I can interpret it as a way of indicating that
at the end of the day I'm okay with it and that
you're doing it on my behalf. But here, you're using my vessel
to give to this woman to marry her. Okay? Since whatever I
say is not interpreted as me being okay, it's going to be
interpreted as being sarcastic. Whoever entitled you to use my vessels to
marry this woman? אבל הכא משום כיסופא דעבד, Aval hacha mishum kisufa
de-avad, and even if I say, oh, you should've used a better
one and there is a better one, we don't interpret that as
me being okay with it. It's because I'm embarrassed on your behalf.
I'm not going to shame you publicly, okay? ואינה מקודשת, v'eina mekudeshes,
it does not work. Whatever I say in this case, we can't
assume that I'm okay with it, you used something that wasn't yours
that you had no right to use. Okay, and so we'll end
with this and we will take up tomorrow with the next משנה.
You have a really...